Finding aid to the Linda Burnham papers SSC.MS.00736
Sophia Smith Collection
Linda Burnham papers
1973-2015
Sophia Smith Collection
Burnham, Linda, 1948-
SSC.MS.00736
4.75 linear feet (6 boxes)
Linda Burnham is a journalist, activist, and leader in women's rights movements, particularly with organizations and projects serving and advocating for women of color. Collection is comprised of photographs, writings by Burnham, and biographical material. Also, in addition to materials and photographs related to the Third World Women Alliance (TWWA), there is also much material related to its successor organizations, the Alliance Against Women's Oppression and the Women of Color Resource Center.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Linda Burnham donated these materials to the Sophia Smith collection in 2015 (accession 2015-S-0001) and 2018 (Accession 2018-S-0023).
Biographical Note
Linda Burnham is a journalist, activist, and leader in women's rights movements, particularly with organizations and projects serving and advocating for women of color.
Burnham was born in 1948 to parents who were active in the Young Communist League in the 1930s and 1940s. She grew up in Brooklyn, New York and graduated from Reed College in 1968. As a journalist and political activist, Burnham has been involved with the Venceremos Brigades, the Third World Women's Alliance, the Alliance Against Women's Oppression, the Angela Davis Defense Committee, and the Line of March. She co-founded the Women of Color Resource Center in Oakland, California in 1990 and served as its Executive Director for eighteen years. Burnham is currently the National Research Director for the National Domestic Workers Alliance. In 2009, Burnham edited "Changing the Race: Racial Politics and the Election of Barack Obama." Her recent writings focus on women and poverty and on women and militarism. In 2012, she co-authored "Home Economics: The Invisible and Unregulated World of Domestic Work." Her deep commitment to organizing the oppressed has earned her multiple awards. She was nominated in 2005 as one of the 1000 Peace Women for the Nobel Prize and received the Twink Frey Social Activist Award in 2008. She also practices and has taught yoga for decades and has studied African and African diasporic dance.
Related Materials
Materials relevant to researchers in this collection may also be found in the Voices of Feminism Oral History Project, Women of Color Resource Center Records, Alliance Against Women's Oppression Records, and Third World Women's Alliance Records, all of which are held in the Sophia Smith Collection.
Scope and Contents
Collection is comprised of photographs, writings by Burnham, and biographical material. Also, in addition to materials and photographs related to the Third World Women Alliance (TWWA), there is also much material related to its successor organizations, the Alliance Against Women's Oppression and the Women of Color Resource Center. Of particular interest are the TWWA's FBI records obtained in 2005 and the materials associated with their Coalition to Fight Infant Mortality campaign (1978-1982) and to the Somos Hermanas campaign seeking cooperation with Sandanista women in Nicaragua (1984-1987).
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Related Materials
This online finding aid currently provides detailed description of only the most recent additions to this collection. Additional materials are described in unpublished lists that can be sent to you upon request by contacting specialcollections@smith.edu
African American feminists -- Biography -- Sources; African American women -- Employment -- History -- Sources; African American women -- Political activity -- Sources; Asian American -- Social conditions -- History -- Sources; Asian American women -- Civil rights -- History -- Sources; Asian American women -- Social conditions -- History -- Sources; Domestic workers; Hispanic American women -- Biography -- Sources; Hispanic American women -- Social conditions; Housekeeping -- History; Immigrants -- United States -- Social conditions -- Sources; Labor movement -- History -- Sources; Latina women -- Social conditions -- History; Minority women -- Employment -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Minority women -- Employment -- United States -- History; Pacific Islander American women -- -- Social conditions -- History; National Domestic Workers Alliance; Women of Color Resource Center; Burnham, Linda, 1948-; Third World Women's Alliance; Burnham, Linda, 1948-
- Linda Burnham photographs and Third World Women's Alliance records, 1973-2010; Accession 2018-S-0023; 4.5 linear feet (3 record cartons, 1 card file box, 1 OS box)
  Scope and Contents
  In addition to materials and photographs related to the Third World Women Alliance (TWWA), there is also much material related to its successor organizations, the Alliance Against Women's Oppression and the Women of Color Resource Center. Of particular interest are the TWWA's FBI records obtained in 2005 and the materials associated with their Coalition to Fight Infant Mortality campaign (1978-1982) and to the Somos Hermanas campaign seeking cooperation with Sandanista women in Nicaragua (1984-1987).
  Computer media
  - Third World Women's Alliance correspondence, pamphlets, and financial records, 1973-1989 (Box 1)
  - Coalition to Fight Infant Mortality correspondence, reports, flyers, and newspaper articles, 1979-1982 (Box 1)
  - Alliance Against Women's Oppression discussion papers, politics and theory readings, and materials related to the Somos Hermanas and Jesse Jackson for president campaigns, 1981-1989 (Box 1)
  - Women of Color Resource Center notes, publications, TWWA teaching guide and FBI records, event planning, and grant materials, 2001-2008 (Box 1)
  - Women of Color Resource Center By-laws, Sister to Sister newsletter, Sister of Fire Awards programs, invitations, pamphlets, and brochures, 2000-2009 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous materials including brochures of other organizations, newspaper clippings, pamphlets re: women's oppression, 1973-1987 (Box 2)
  - Photographs, negatives, and slides, 1976-2006 (Box 2)
  - DVDs: Women's meeting; "Do Tell: Women of Color Resource Center", April-June, 2009 (Box 2)
  - Women of Color Resource Center photo albums (3), 2002-2006 (Box 2)
  - Women of Color Resource Center photograph albums (4), including "Beijing 1995", 1995-2003 (Box 3)
  - Loose photographs of TWWA, AAWO, and WORC activities, Approximately 1970-2000 (Box 4)
  - 4 CDs: Photographs, including 3 of the Independence Day 2004 programming, 2004-2005 (Box 4)
  - 3.5 floppy disks (2): "Welfare Module Wedge contents" and Photographs, Approximately 1995-2010 (Box 4)
  - Posters and T-shirts (Box 5)